大人们 我得承认
My lords, I do confess to you that.
尽管过去几周来
Although I have lain with the queen.
我几乎夜夜与王后同床
almost every night these past weeks,
但我的良知却不允许我履行婚姻的实质
My conscience will not permit me to consummate this marriage.
因为我认为这场婚姻存有缺陷
because I feel there is some impediment to it.
我已尽我所能地努力说服自己
I have done as much as any man.
从感情上从理智上接受
to move the consent of my heart and mind,
但良知上的负担却怎么也无法排除
But the obstacle will not out of my thoughts.
可能是因为
Perhaps the truth is that there existed a.
洛林公爵之子与公主有婚约在先
Precontract between the duke of lorraine's son and the Princess after all,
而且这层关系从未解除 因此
from which she was never released, And so therefore.
我实际上是娶了位有夫之妇
I am really married to another man's wife.
大人们
My lords,
此事交由你们去审查
I leave it to you.
看看我是否多虑了
to investigate whether or not my scruples are justified.
陛下
your majesty.
大人 您必须为陛下的良知找个开脱之法
my lord, you must find some way to relieve his majesty's conscience.
说实话 查尔斯
I tell you, charles,
如果这场婚姻维持下去
God will not grant me any more children.
上帝是不会再赐予我孩子的
if I continue in this marriage.
她果真如此无知 不知道新婚之夜该做什么
Was she such a maid that she didn't know what to do?
一个对大婚之夜不谙就里的女人
Not telling a woman what she must expect on her wedding night.
就如同不带干粮直接出海的水手
is like sending a sailor to sea with no biscuit.
我会勒令柯伦威尔设法解除这个婚姻
I will force cromwell to bring about a dissolution of the marriage.
原本我只是为了国家的安危
I only went ahead with it for the sake of.
可如今这个理由已经无意义
The realm and now even that reason is forgot.
罗马皇帝和法国国王又一次决裂
The emperor and the king of france are at each other's throats again.
而且都要来求爱 现在谁还需要克里维斯
and both have come courting. who needs cleves?
这场婚姻不是克伦威尔大人的主意么
my lord cromwell. was the match not his idea?
王后陛下 玛丽公主到
majesty, the princess mary is here.
公主殿下 请坐
princess, if you please.
我收到了一位表兄弟的来函
I have received a letter from a cousin of mine.
巴伐利亚的菲利浦公爵
He is duke philip of bavaria.
菲利普打算来英国向您求爱
Philip would like to come to england and pay court to you.
为什么
why?
他听说了许多关于您的事 玛丽公主
he has heard many things about you, princess mary.
很多善事
Many good things.
我想他应该是路德教徒的 和您一样
I suppose he's a lutheran, like you?
他很有魅力长得也英俊
he is charming and very good looking.
我想您应该会喜欢他的
I think you might like him a little.
- 我要对他怎么说 - 就说
- What shall I tell him? - tell him…
就说只要他愿意并且国王准许 他可以来
Tell him he may come if he pleases and if the king wishes.
但别抱太大期望
But not to expect anything.
父亲
father?
格里高利
gregory!
你来这儿干吗
What on earth are you doing here?
你见您把药片落在药剂师那儿了
well, I noticed you forgot your pills at the apothecary.
不希望您受痛
I didn't want you to be in pain.
坐
sit down.
最近忙什么呢
so what are you working on?
我在为议会准备关于医疗行业的法案
I'm preparing some bills for parliament on the medical profession.
我还试着说服陛下
And I'm trying to persuade his majesty to.
根据其政绩任命官员 就这些
Appoint councillors based upon merit, and nothing else.
您看上去很累 父亲
you look tired, father.
- 陛下怎么样 - 他还好
- How is his majesty? - he's fine.
他的腿病困扰着他 疼的时候 他就会暴躁
His leg bothers him; it gets sore. he gets irritable.
所以他有时就拿您撒气
is that why he strikes you on the head sometimes?
我不怨国王 但其他人却在想法推倒我
I resent the king nothing, but others seek to undermine me,
因为我出身如此卑微 而他们如此高贵
Since I was born so low and they so high…
当然 还有其他原因
And for other reasons too.
别太在意
Think not on that.
照顾好你的妻子 以及她腹中的胎儿
Look after your own dear wife, and the child in her belly.
如爱上帝及上帝的旨意般爱他们 就会没事的
Love them as you love god and his holy word, and all shall be well.
很遗憾您没能抓到那个狡猾的叛徒雷金纳德·珀尔
I'm sorry you failed to capture that arch traitor reginald pole,
弗朗西斯爵士
Sir francis.
国王对他恨之入骨
The king detests him above all men.
不过 他现在正受另一件事的困扰
However, he has other matters on his mind now.
上次同陛下谈话时他告诉我 他对他目前的生活
When I last spoke to his majesty he confessed he was, in some ways,
- 多少有些厌倦 - 是生活还是他妻子
- Tired with his life. - his life or his wife?
基本上是一回事
they are much the same thing.
他就不能找点乐子么 就像从前那样
can he not find distraction, as he has always done before?
这是不难 但他比以往难伺候了
easily. but he is more jaded than before.
过去的那些已不再配他的胃口
The usual remedies won't suit.
得要更 极致的 才能吸引他
Something more… extreme… might tempt him.
至少在这种事上 公爵大人 我不会让陛下失望的
In this matter at least, your grace, I shall not fail the king.
小姐
My lady.
先生
Sir?
玛丽公主 请恕我冒昧
Princess mary, I hope you can forgive my impetuosity.
我们本当彼此正式介绍的
I know we should have been formally introduced, but…
- 但我等不及了 - 您就是菲利普公爵
- I couldn't wait. - you are duke philip?
我能亲吻您的手么
may I kiss your hand?
希望能再次见到您 小姐
I hope I might see you again, my lady.
当然 有我的表姐王后在场
With my cousin the queen present, of course.
我本打算明天回乡下的
I had thought to leave court tomorrow for the country.
不过我可以推迟行程 如果这能使您欢喜的话
I may delay my leaving, if it pleases you.
一或两天
For a day or so.
兰贝斯宫 伦敦
我亲爱的弗朗西斯 我太想您了|my sweet francis, I missed you!
还是那么英俊
Handsome as ever.
好久没见您了 最近在忙什么
We haven't seen you for ages. what have you been doing?
- 忙着去杀人 - 成功了么
- trying to kill someone. - did you manage it?
还没有
not yet.
我想您是来看望我的小可爱们的吧
I suppose you've come to look over my little darlings?
那也得让我先把您看个够 我亲爱的夫人
only after I've feasted my eyes on you, my dear lady.
去你的 最近来了几位新姑娘
go along. we have some new ones, I think.
漂亮的小东西
Pretty little things.
我有时简直难以相信
I sometimes find it hard to believe that whoever.
她们的父母怎么能狠心丢弃她们
Bore them did not feel bothered or obliged to raise them.
您不是说她们多数是私生子
you told me most of them were bastards.
但那是贵族的私生子 我可爱的孩子
but aristocratic bastards, my sweet boy.
贵族私生子
Aristocratic bastards.
给娃娃做条裙子
Make a dress for our doll.
我想我之前见过他
I think I've seen him here before.
- 他是谁 - 不知道
- who do you think he is? - I don't know.
你说他跟人斗过剑么
do you think he's been in a sword fight?
是么
Do you think he was?
我找到能取悦陛下的人了
I have found someone to amuse the king.
她是谁
who is she?
她叫凯瑟琳·霍华德
her name is miss katherine howard.
她是诺福克公爵的远亲
She is a distant relation to the duke of norfolk.
她的出身 怎么说呢
Her background is… how shall I say?
不是真正意义的高贵血统
Not entirely conventional.
我想她一定年轻貌美
I assume she's young and pretty.
自己看吧 大人们
see for yourself, my lord.
你可以进来了
You may come in now.
凯瑟琳 这两位就是我跟你说过的大人物
Katherine, these are the excellent people I told you of.
萨福克公爵大人 赫特福德伯爵大人
His grace, the duke of suffolk, and the earl of hertford.
两位大人
your graces.
你多大了 凯瑟琳
how old are you, katherine?
我十七岁
seventeen.
我想知道是谁教她数数的
I wonder who taught her to count.
说说你自己 你的家庭情况 等等
tell us something about yourself. your family. so on.
母亲在我很小的时候就已去世
my mother died when I was little.
父亲续弦 但我和继母感情疏淡
My father remarried, but I didn't know his wife really.
我被送去孀居的公爵夫人家
I was sent to live in the household of the dowager duchess.
那应该是诺福克的遗孀公爵夫人
that would be the dowager duchess of norfolk?
- 二世公爵的孀妻 - 我想是的 大人
- The widow of the second duke - I suppose so, my lord.
我跟她见面不多
I didn't see her much.
那儿还有好多孩子 来自各类婚姻状况
There were other children there, from lots of marriages.
我们玩得可疯了 很有趣呢
We ran a little wild. there was some fun in it.
凯瑟琳宝贝儿
well, sweet katherine,
我看你又可以开始找乐了
I think the fun is just about to start again.
您觉得怎样 公爵大人
what do you think, your grace?
我看嘛
I think…
我看她挺合国王口味
I think she looks fit for a king.
这么说 您跟他 跟菲利浦说过话了
so, did you talk to him? to philip?
是啊 说了几句
a little. yes.
我相信他是个聪明的小伙
I believe he is a very intelligent young man.
我不能确定
I couldn't tell.
而且十分俊俏
and extremely good-looking.
他对您十分倾心哪
he likes you a great deal.
他几乎都还不认识我
he doesn't even know me.
我们没有任何共同点
we have nothing in common.
陛下 菲利浦公爵请求接见
your majesty, duke philip asks for an audience.
- 我可不想见他 - 那到里边去 快
- I don't want to see him. - then go in there! quickly.
菲利浦 我亲爱的表弟
Ah, philip. my dear cousin.
陛下
majesty.
您觉得这个国家如何
how do you find this country?
我很喜欢英国
I like it very much.
住在这里一定会很愉快
I could most happily live here.
这么说 您见到过玛丽公主了
so, you've met princess mary?
虽然只有一面之缘
it was only for a moment,
可那时的情景总在脑海中不断重演
But I relive that moment over and over again in my mind.
此前我听闻她彬彬有礼
I was told before that she was charming,
机智过人 博览群书 和蔼可亲
intelligent, well-read, gracious.
是阿拉贡的凯瑟琳王后之嫡女
The true heir of katherine of aragon.
一位真正的公主
A true princess.
可我没想到她如此美丽
But nothing prepared me for her beauty.
她的美丽发自内心
But a beauty that comes from inside.
对我而言 她是这世间最美的女子
To me, she is the most beautiful creature on god's earth.
枢密院已遵照陛下的旨意
the council has acted upon your majesty's request.
向王后的公使索要其此前与洛林公爵之子
We demanded written evidence of the queen's envoy about.
婚约之书面文件
The pre-marriage contract to the duke of lorraine's son.
他们已交付 可据文件所载
They provided it, but the papers seem to suggest that,
与通常所用的措辞 婚约承诺 不同
Instead of the usual formula, "per verba de futuro",
文件中的准确措辞为 即时生效婚约
The actual wording on the document reads "per verba de presenti",
就是说该婚约具有法律约束力 不能解除
which is a binding contract which renunciation cannot undo.
这么说 陛下尽可放心
so it does seem that your majesty has reason to be optimistic.
国王注意到你了 他也许会要见你
the king has noticed you. he may ask to see you.
我该跟他说什么 我该怎么做
what shall I say to him? what should I do?
做你自己
just be yourself.
那女孩子是谁
who is that girl?
那是凯瑟琳·霍华德
that is katherine howard.
诺福克公爵家的远亲
She is a relation to the duke of norfolk.
进宫没多久
She has only just come to court.
带她来见我
bring her to me.
遵旨
majesty.
陛下 凯瑟琳·霍华德小姐到
Majesty, miss katherine howard.
谢谢 查尔斯
thank you, charles.
凯瑟琳
Katherine.
陛下
your majesty.
请 来这坐
please, be seated here.
您嫁人了吗
Are you married?
没有 陛下
no, your majesty.
识字吗
can you read?
- 能写信 - 谁给你写信
- enough to write a letter. - who writes to you?
没人
nobody.
拥有很多房产吗
do you have many houses?
- 我去 - 怎么了
- ouch! - what is it?
您踩着我了
you stepped on my foot.
菲利浦 我很抱歉
philip, I'm so very sorry!
我向您道歉 真对不起
I do apologize. I'm so sorry.
菲利浦 我真抱歉
Philip, I'm so sorry!
- 我以为 - 您没踩着我
- I thought… - you didn't step on my foot.
怎么可能呢 您脚步轻盈几乎不沾地
How could you? your feet don't even touch the ground.
我想和您单独在一起
I wanted a moment alone with you.
我
I…
您哭了
You're crying.
那是因为我太快乐了
only because I'm so happy.
我能再亲您一次吗
would you like me to kiss you again?
知道这个戒指的渊源吗
do you know where this ring comes from?
曾被陈列在肯特布雷大教堂的
It once adorned.
托马斯·拜科特主教神坛里
the shrine of thomas becket at canterbury.
整个神坛珠光宝气 摆满各国王室与朝圣者的供品
The whole shrine glittered with jewels, left by princes and pilgrims.
但这戒指
But this ring…
这戒指是最珍贵的供品
This ring was the most valuable gift of all.
一位法国国王贡献出此物
A king of france left it as an offering.
只为他的灵魂得到救赎
to save his mortal soul.
我能摸一下吗
may I touch it?
晚安 公主殿下
good night, princess.
晚安 公爵大人
good night, your grace.
告诉我 克伦威尔先生
tell me, mr. cromwell,
无双宫建造进度怎么样
how is work proceeding on my palace at nonsuch?
我高兴地回禀 宫殿即将建造完成
I am pleased to report that it is almost complete,
七月里您就可以巡视进度
And will be ready for your personal inspection come july.
很好
good.
我要送块土地给凯瑟琳·霍华德小姐
I want to give a gift of land to mistress katherine howard.
最近我们查抄了个罪犯的财产
There is some we recently confiscated from a felon.
要是我没记错 那块地上还有两栋大宅
If I remember correctly. with two large houses upon it?
我希望将之全部赐给霍华德小姐
I wish to grant the whole to mistress howard.
陛下
majesty.
听说枢密院已找到王后前次婚约里的纰漏
I hear the council found a flaw in the queen's precontract.
如果王后本人否认该项婚约
It was not such a flaw that it could not.
这个纰漏也未必有用
Be overcome by the queen's personal repudiation.
但应该还是有法可依
there must still be grounds.
看在上帝的份上 我不认为她是我的合法妻子
Before god, I think she is not my lawful wife.
克伦威尔先生 不论人前人后
Whatever people say,
众人怎么议论您
mr.Cromwell, either to your face or behind your back,
您依然是我枢密院的首席大臣
You are still my first minister,
我既没有理由也没有必要怀疑您的爱与忠诚
Whose love and loyalty I have no cause nor reason to doubt.
有任何军国大事要处理
If there is anything important to be done,
我知道谁是最佳人选
I know who best to do it.
陛下
majesty.
- 克伦威尔先生 - 先生 克伦威尔先生
- mr. cromwell! - mr. cromwell, sir!
- 克伦威尔先生 - 卫斯李先生
- mr. cromwell! - mr. risley.
- 交给卫斯李先生 - 我们会尽力
- Give it to mr. risley - we're doing our best.
好的 很好 很好
very good, very good, very good.
- 卫斯李先生 谢谢您 先生 - 谢谢 谢谢
- mr. risley! thank you sir. - thank you. thank you.
陛下
your majesty.
与法国大使的会晤如何
how was your meeting with the french ambassador?
很有意思 陛下
it was very interesting, your majesty.
他告诉我法国国王
He told me that the king was not.
已不再反对同我方秘密协商
Averse to opening secret negotiations with us.
旨在脱离与罗马皇帝
With a view to disengaging the french from.
那不太令人满意的联盟
Their disagreeable alliance with the emperor.
很好
Good.
大使先生还说 如果没有克伦威尔大人从中作梗
The ambassador also suggested to me how much anglo-french relations.
英法关系势必会大大改善
Would improve if lord cromwell no longer stood as an obstacle to them.
霍华德小姐
mistress howard?
国王要您收下这个礼物
The king would like you to accept a gift.
太美了
it's lovely.
您得谢谢陛下
You must thank his majesty.
您可以自己去谢他
you can thank him yourself.
陛下
your majesty.
进来
come.
加德纳主教 就等您呢
Bishop gardiner. just the man we needed.
现在 我们可以开始了
Now, we may begin.
格里高利 怎么了
gregory? what is it?
是个男孩 我有儿子了
it's a boy. I have a son.
感谢上帝
thanks be to god…
爱德华王子到 陛下
prince edward, your majesty.
吾儿
my son.
我儿
My son.
- 先生们 我召集此次议会会议是为了… - 克伦威尔
- gentlemen, I call this council meeting to order…- cromwell,
别坐在那儿
Do not sit there.
这儿没有你的座位
That is no place for you.
叛国贼没资格同绅士们坐在一起
Traitors do not sit among gentlemen.
克伦威尔大人 您因叛国罪被捕
my lord cromwell, you are arrested for treason.
我不是叛国贼
I am no traitor.
我问你们 凭你们的良心 我是不是叛国贼
I ask you, on your consciences, am I a traitor?
- 是的 叛国贼 叛国贼 - 叛国贼 叛国贼
- yes! traitor! traitor! - traitor! traitor!
- 叛国贼 叛国贼 - 叛国贼
- traitor! traitor! - traitor!
我不是叛国贼 我不是
I am no traitor! I am no traitor!
我不是叛国贼
I'm no traitor!
不 不 不 不
No… no, no. no!
我不是叛国贼
I'm no traitor!
玛丽公主 请坐下
princess mary, do sit down.
我有 有一个消息
I have some… some news.
菲利普公爵已被遣返回巴伐利亚
Duke philip has been sent back to bavaria.
您父亲 国王 送他走的 我很遗憾 我不能解释
Your father, the king, sent him away. I am so sorry. I cannot explain.
没必要解释 这无关紧要
no need to explain. it is of little matter.
公爵很温柔 但我不可能嫁给他
The duke was charming but I would never have married him.
他是路德会教徒 而我是天主教徒
He is a lutheran and I am a catholic.
各位大人
my lords,
我特来此提出一项弹劾托马斯·克伦威尔的议案
I am come here to introduce a bill of.
指控他犯有叛国罪
Attainder against thomas cromwell on a charge of treason.
克伦威尔大人
Lord cromwell,
出身极其卑微 受到了陛下的大力提拔
Whom his majesty has raised from a very base and low degree,
获得陛下的慷慨馈赠
And enriched with manifold gifts.
却被证实是个最为不忠腐坏的叛国者和欺诈犯
is proved to be a most false and corrupt traitor and deceiver.
叛国贼 叛国贼 叛国贼
Traitor! traitor! traitor!
他是一名恶劣的异教分子
being a detestable heretic,
极力怂恿撺掇
He has utterly disposed to set and sow common.
在陛下忠诚的子民们中煽动叛乱
Sedition among your majesty's loyal and loving subjects.
作为负责宗教改革的副执事 克伦威尔
As the vice-regent for religion supposed to oversee reform, cromwell has,
在陛下不知情的情况下 许可异教分子传教布道
Without his majesty's knowledge, licensed heretics to preach and teach.
各位大人 我们有确实证据 三月三十一日当晚
My lords, we have evidence that on the night of march the 31st,
在圣彼得平民教区
In the parish of st.Peter the poor,
克伦威尔大人目中无人地替那些异教传教士辩解
Lord cromwell did arrogantly defend these heretic preachers.
他说即使国王反对改革 他也不会
He said if the king should turn against reform, he would not turn.
如果国王及其追随者果真反对
And if the king did turn, and all his followers,
那他将会手执利剑起来战斗
Then he would stand fighting in the field with his sword in his hand,
反抗国王和他的追随者们
Against the king and against all his followers.
然后他取出他的短剑 他说
And he took out his dagger, and he said,
若我不会为纷争而死
"or let this dagger thrust me to the heart,
那就让这柄短剑刺穿我的心脏
"if I would not die for that quarrel.
如若令我多活上一或两年
"and if I should live a year or two,
那我不会再替国王效命
"then it will no longer be in the king's.
阻止或妨碍改革的进行
Power any more to resist or hinder our reformation."
然后他发下一个重誓
And he swore a great oath!
叛国贼 叛徒 叛国贼 叛国贼
Traitor! traitor! traitor! traitor!
您爱这个人 这是不是真的 理查德爵士
is it true that you loved this man, sir richard?
作为朋友
as a friend.
但我爱他主要是因为 我以为我看到
But I chiefly loved him for the love I thought.
他爱陛下胜于一切
I saw him bear towards the king above all others.
但现在 如果他是个叛徒
But now, if he be a traitor,
那我很遗憾我曾爱他信任他
Then I am sorry that I ever loved him or trusted him,
而且我很高兴他的叛国罪及时地被揭露了
And I am very glad that his treason is discovered in time.
叛国贼 叛国贼 制裁
Traitor! traitor! justice!
我相信 夫人 您在此很愉快也被招待得很好吧
I trust, madam, you are happy and well treated?
我没有任何可挑剔的
I have no complaints whatsoever.
我走到哪里都获得了
Everywhere I go I am treated with.
众人的尊敬和友善的对待
Great respect and kindness from everyone.
我很高兴
I'm glad.
您不吃么
You are not eating.
陛下
your majesty…
- 我… 我想知道 - 我要把您送到我在里士满的
- I… I wondered… - I am sending you away for a while,
宫殿待一阵子
To my palace at richmond.
为了您的健康 和您的愉悦心情
For your health, and for your pleasure.
谢谢您 陛下
thank you, your majesty.
我有要事亟待处理
I have some urgent business to attend to.
夫人
Madam.
您作为教廷的首脑 议会认为您有权
the council considers it sufficient, as head of the church,
勒令主教宣告您的婚姻无效
That you can have the bishops annul your union.
但出于外交考虑 最好您能找到证据证明
But it would be more diplomatic if you should find proof that the.
您的婚姻并未正式生效
Marriage was never consummated and that.
并且陛下你也从未真正认可过它
Your majesty never truly consented to it.
派代表去见克伦威尔先生
send a deputation to mr. cromwell.
要求他出具书面证明支持我废除婚姻
Demand of him written evidence supporting my annulment.
无疑他该记得我多次向他提到
Doubtless he'll remember how often I spoke.
我有多么厌恶那个女人
To him of how my nature abhors that woman…
克伦威尔先生
mr. cromwell.
公爵大人
your grace.
国王命令您为他写封信
the king orders that you write him a letter,
描述他是如何看待克里维斯的安
Describing how he found anne of cleves,
他关于此事是如何向您交待的
What passed between you on that subject.
以及他是否告诉过您
and whether he told you.
在场所谓的婚姻里 他有没有真正圆过房
he had consummated his so-called marriage or not.
他还命令您描述此项婚姻之纰漏
He also orders you to describe the impediments to the marriage,
以及明知纰漏的情况下 仍执意安排了联姻
And whether knowing them you still arranged it.
陛下责令您
His majesty charges that,
由于您在严酷的审判之日将面对上帝
As you will answer god on the dreadful day of judgment,
您的灵魂与良知都已极端危险必遭天谴
And also upon the extreme danger and damnation of your soul and conscience.
把您知道的都明确写下来
to write down exactly what you know.
我会愉悦地谨尊皇命
I will most gladly do as the king commands.
只要国王能欢喜和满意
I trust to his pleasure and satisfaction.
我希求国王的舒心比什么都紧要
I desire more than anything else the king's comfort,
为此捐躯也在所不辞
And would most willingly die for it.
不知道从这扇窗能否看到您的宅邸
I wondered if you could see your house from that window?
事实是 克伦威尔先生
The fact is, mr.Cromwell,
在您被捕仅两小时后
That only two hours after your arrest the king.
国王便派遣司库去清缴了您的财产
Dispatched his treasurer there to take away your goods.
一群乌合之众拥出来欢呼雀跃
The rabble came out to cheer them on.
听说 那场景可热闹了
It was a pretty sight, I hear.
卫兵
Guard.
在知道陛下对此安排并不如我所预想的那么满意时
"finding your majesty not as pleased "as I trusted to have done,
我仍斗胆向您问询对皇后的感受
I was so bold "to ask you how you liked the queen.
陛下严肃地答道 你知道
"your majesty soberly answered, ""as you know,
我以前就不甚喜欢她 现在愈加厌恶
I liked her not well before, "but now I like her much worse.
我触摸过她的腹部和胸部 因而
"i have felt her belly and her breasts "and thereby, as I can judge,
我能判断她不是处女
She should be no maid.
我让她来时什么样就是什么样
I left her as good a maid as I found her!""
最后呢 他最后写了什么
at the end. what does he say at the end?
我谦恭地恳求陛下见谅
"i beseech your majesty most humbly "to.
我这封粗陋的来信 并请您了解
Pardon my rude writing and to consider that I,
我 这个最悲伤的囚犯 做好了受死的准备
A most woeful prisoner, am ready to take the death,
只要能博得上帝和您的欢心就好
When it shall please god and your majesty."
但是我这孱弱的躯壳却迫使我不断向您乞求您的怜悯
Yet the frail flesh incites me continually to call to your grace for.
宽恕我的罪 乞求基督的拯救和保护
Mercy and grace for my offences, and thus christ save,
愿上帝与您同在
preserve, and keep you…
写于伦敦塔 6月30日 六月最后一个星期三
written at the tower this wednesday, …
藉由一颗沉重的心和颤抖的手
The last of june with heavy heart and trembling hand of.
陛下您最可悲的囚犯和仆人敬上
Your highness' most heavy and miserable prisoner and poor slave.
信的最下面他还写了些东西
He's written something right down at the bottom.
最仁慈的君主啊 求您发发慈悲 慈悲
"most gracious prince, I cry for mercy, mercy.
发发慈悲
Mercy."
大人您明天会去塔山吗
will your grace be on tower hill tomorrow?
别算上我
try to keep me away.
我可以向大人承诺
I can vouchsafe to your grace his.
他的结局绝对是最屈辱的
Final end will be the most ignominious ever.
我听到了 大人 听到了
so I have heard, your grace. so I have heard.
他是什么意思 告诉我
what is he talking about? tell me.
克伦威尔会在亨格福特大人 也就是疯子沃尔特
cromwell is set to appear on the same scaffold as lord hungerford…
被处死的同一个断头台上受刑
Otherwise known as mad walter,
那人被控多项罪名被判死刑 比如鸡奸
Who has been sentenced to death for various offences such as sodomy,
强奸自己的女儿
Raping his daughter.
让术师们预测国王的死期
and paying magicians to predict the date of the king's death.
至少他不用费心为预测自己的死期付钱
at least he won't have to pay them to predict the date of his own.
那么克伦威尔会很丢脸的
then cromwell will be humiliated.
这个恶劣的下等人 狼子野心害了多少人
The false churl who was so ambitious for others' blood!
我们的手段还不止这些
ah, that is not our only device.
汤姆和我还想出更绝的 让那位大大尝尝
Tom and I have conceived some more sport at his lordship's expense.
什么主意
what kind of sport?
耐心点儿 爱德华
patience edward.
耐心点儿
Patience.
再来一罐啤酒
let's have another beer.
抱歉 我忘了你的名字了 朋友
Sorry, there; I've forgotten your name, fellow.
- 是什么来着 - 先生 是格利亚
- What is it again? - gurrea, sir.
格利亚 你生过梅毒还是好了 俄利亚
gurrea. d'you have the pox or is it gone, 'urrea?
明天有重要的事
It's a big day tomorrow.
我应该去睡觉了
I ought to be abed.
最后一品脱 我请客
a last pint! I'm paying.
让我们再为老朋友喝一杯
And then let's drink to old friends, huh?
另外来两品脱 伙计
Two more pints, my good man!
格利亚师傅 我相信你今早已经清醒了吧
master gurrea, I trust you're feeling clear- headed this morning.
夫人 哈特福德伯爵觐见
Madam, the earl of hartford is come.
各位大人
my lords.
夫人 我特来向您通知 议会
madam, it is my duty to inform you that parliament,
坎特伯雷和约克的正式会议
The convocations of canterbury and york.
确认您与国王的婚姻无效
have found your marriage to the king to be invalid.
鉴于您和洛林家有婚约在先
on the grounds Of your precontract with lorraine,
国王亦不赞同这桩婚事 并且你们没有圆房
his majesty's lack of consent to the marriage, and its non-consummation.
这桩婚姻特此宣告无效
The marriage is thus declared null and void,
自此以后 若您自称为他的妹妹
And from henceforth it is the king's.
国王将十分欣喜
Pleasure that you call yourself his sister.
您赞同吗
Do you consent?
这样的话
In which case,
我可以告诉您 国王给您准备了多达4000英镑的年金
I can tell you that the king has settled upon you a handsome annuity of 4, 000 pounds per annum.
并赠予您布莱彻和里士满的庄园以及希威城堡
as well as the manors of bletchingly and richmond, and also hever castle.
只要您在英国就都是您的
so long as you remain in england.
由于国王确认您仍是处女
And since his majesty confirms that you are still a maid,
您可以自行择偶
You are free to marry whom you choose.
请您
please…
告诉国王
Tell the king that…
我希望有朝一日能有幸再见他的尊面
I hope I will sometimes have the pleasure of his most noble presence,
并祈求全能的主能够保佑他长寿和健康
And beseech the almighty to send him long life and good health.
女士
oh, my lady.
父亲
father!
Father.
好人们啊 我来此是受死的
good people, I am come here to die,
不是为洗脱我的罪 尽管有人认为我该这样做
and not to purge myself, as some may think I should.
我被依法判处死刑
I am by law condemned to die and I thank my lord.
感谢我主对我的犯下的罪赐予死刑
God that has granted me this death for my offence.
因为我长久以来冒犯了上帝 是个罪人
For since I came of age I have lived as a sinner.
我衷心祈求得到祂的宽恕
and offended my lord god for which I ask him heartily for forgiveness.
闭嘴吧 看到上帝的份儿上 闭嘴受死吧
get it over with! for christ's sake, get it over with!
我也冒犯了我的君王 为此我恳求他的宽恕
I have also offended my prince, for which I ask him hearty amnesty.
我衷心希望你们能为国王祈福
I heartily desire you to pray for the king's grace and.
希望他能健康富足地和你们生活在一起
That he may long live with you in health and prosperity.
继他之后 他的儿子 爱德华王子能长久统治你们
And that after him his son, prince edward, may long reign over you.
就是这儿了 无双宫
there it is. nonsuch palace.
我的小丑告诉我 它不存在
My fool told me it didn't exist.
先生们 你们应该从我这里得到警示
gentlemen, you should all take warning from me, who was, as you know,
我从一介草民受到国王的提拔
who was, as you know, from a poor man made by the prince.
成为了举足轻重的重臣
into a great gentleman and that i, not contented with that,
我却仍不满足 不满于王国由我治理
not with having the kingdom at my orders.
仍不停寻求更高的地位
presumed to a still higher state.
我的自大最终带来了惩罚
my pride has brought its punishment.
上帝啊 当我的双眼不能视物
Lord, grant me that when these eyes shall lose their use,
请赐予我灵魂的双眼使我能看到您
The eyes of my soul may see thee.
上帝天父啊 当我的嘴失去作用
God lord and father, that when this mouth shall lose his use…
杀了他
kill him!
我的心能说话 天父 我将灵魂放予您的手中
that my heart that say to thee father, into your hands I commend my spirit.
快啊 杀了他
come on now! take his head off!
为国王 议会大臣们祈祷
pray for the prince and for the lords of the council,
为牧师们以及人民祈祷
and for the clergy and for the people.
我现在再次请求你们也会为我祈祷
Now I beg you again that you will pray for me.
祈祷 可以的话 我能一击毙命
Pray, if possible, cut off the head with one blow…
这样我就不用太痛苦
That I may not suffer much.
砍头
chop it off!
陛下
your majesty.